CURRICULUM VITAE WANGILA Abraham Masinde

Email: abrahamwangila@gmail.com Phone: +254 711447289

Biological data

• Date of Birth: 30th June, 1987;

Nationality: Kenyan of ID no. 25531264;

• Gender: male;

Marital status: married;

- Languages: Fluent writing and speech in English, Swahili and Luhya;
- Hobbies: blogging (abrahamwangila.wordpress.com), reading, playing basketball and, travelling.

Qualifications Summary

I am an Environment, Health and Safety (EHS) professional with project management experience spanning about seven years. I also have a Bachelor of Science Degree in Environmental Science earned in 2011 with several short-term training courses to deepen and widen my scope of knowledge and skills. I am well read; passionate about enforcement and implementation and; have thorough understanding of Occupational Health and Safety as well as environmental laws, procedures and standards applicable in different sectors including, but not limited to, the Construction, Transport and Logistics, Manufacturing, Hotel and; Oil & Gas industries.

Education

- NEBOSH International General Certificate in Health and Safety (Ongoing)
- Bachelor of Science in Environmental Science (Second Class Honours-Upper Division) from Kenyatta University (2011)
- KCSE B+ from Kibabii Boys High School, Bungoma (2005)

Workshops and Trainings

- Participant, Africa NGO and CSO Chemical Safety Skillshare and Workshop, Dar Es Salaam (December 2013)
- Training on Drug and substance abuse in relation to HIV/AIDS by Pwani University and the National AIDS Control Council, Kenya
- Training on national peace and reconciliation issues by Pwani University College, Kenya*
- Impact of Social Change: UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities (UNCRPD) as a Trigger held at Pwani University (June, 2011).
- Participation in the Call for Proposals Restitution and Lessons Sharing Workshop in Mombasa funded by the European Union (August, 2011).
- Participation in the Right to Food advocacy workshop at the Multimedia University in Nairobi by FIAN Nov, 2011
- Training workshop on Human Rights Based Approach to programming for three days (May 2012). The workshop was organized by UNDP's Amkeni Wakenya Facility in Eldoret, Kenya.

Memberships and affiliations

- Environment Institute of Kenya
- FIAN International For the right to adequate food
- IPEN

Page | 1

- The WaterNetwork.org
- NEMA Environmental Impact Assessment and Audit Expert number 7018

Key Competencies

• Environmental Management Systems management

Page | 2

- Environmental Impact Assessment and Auditing
- Occupational Health and Safety Systems Management, Auditing and Training
- Risk assessment
- Incident investigation
- Energy Systems management
- Budgeting and Budgets Management
- Communication including report writing, documentation and presentation
- Project/program monitoring, evaluation and learning
- Community vocational and workplace training
- Stakeholder mobilization and teams' coordination
- Research including data collection, analysis, interpretation and presentation - with expert knowledge of MS Excel and proficiency in SPSS
- Marketing

Professional Experience

March 2017 to date: Enterprise Générale Malta Forrest (EGMF), Health, Safety, Security and Environment (HSSE) Officer- Lake Turkana Wind Power Project and the 400KV Loyangalani-Suswa Transmission Line

Kev achievements/duties

- 1. Continuously reviewed and developed all aspects of the site's Health and Safety Policy and activity, and enforce policies to establish a culture of Health and Safety at the LTWP and the Transmission Line sites
- 2. Worked proactively with managers and other key staff to establish and maintain a programme of continuous improvement in the management of Health and Safety within their areas of responsibility on the construction site
- Conducted rigorous risk assessments; and accident/incident management systems are in place, undertaking risk assessment processes to identify hazards and ensure appropriate control measures are in place
- 4. Provided staff with comprehensive and relevant information and training on Health and Safety systems and procedures, especially through posters and other signages, toolbox talks and training.
- 5. Maintained the accident, incident and near miss register, investigated accidents or incidents to discover causes and handle workers compensation claims
- 6. Managed firefighting equipment, undertook the planning and implementation of fire drills and other evacuation procedures

- 7. Inspected equipment and machinery to observe possible unsafe conditions, kept maintenance records, ensured that all statutory inspections are conducted
- 8. Maintained a central record of all risk assessments, report on health and safety awareness, issues and statistics.

Page | 3

9. Ensured that appropriate records are maintained in compliance with legal requirements, and that necessary notices are displayed and reviewed.

September 2017 to November 2017: Bollore Transport and Logistics Company Ltd; QHSE Supervisor → Kenya Breweries Limited Site

Key achievements/duties

- 1. Reviewed and enforced policies of Bollore related to Quality, Health, Safety and Environment to build and enrich the workplace culture
- 2. Conducted risk assessments to all new and non-routine activities
- 3. Managed company resources relevant to Health and Safety through regular inspections and keeping of registers including first aid boxes, ladders and firefighting equipment
- 4. Provided staff with comprehensive and relevant information and training on Health and Safety systems and procedures, especially through posters and other signages, toolbox talks and training.
- 5. Maintained the accident, incident and near miss register, investigated accidents or incidents to discover causes and handle workers compensation claims
- 6. Managed firefighting equipment, undertook the planning and implementation of fire drills and other evacuation procedures
- 7. Inspected equipment and machinery to observe possible unsafe conditions, kept maintenance records, ensured that all statutory inspections are conducted
- 8. Maintained a central record of all risk assessments, report on health and safety awareness, issues and statistics.
- 9. Ensured that appropriate records are maintained in compliance with legal requirements, and that necessary notices are displayed and reviewed.

• February 2016 - January 2017: Independent Environment Health Safety Consultant

Key Achievements

- 10. Managed to establish and sustain working relationships with about ten construction contractors and five industrial clients
- 11. Conducted and participated in over fifty Environmental Impact Assessment/ Audit projects
- 12. Conducted and participated in over fifty Noise measurement surveys, Fire Risk Surveys and occupational health and safety audit and training projects

- 13. Established cooperative relationships with Occupational Health and Safety Auditors, Energy Auditors and other EIA/Audit Experts
- *14.* Maintained a strong online presence for marketing purposes and for participation in EHS debates.

• May 2015 to-January 2016: CAST (Appropriate Technology Development Centre), Food Safety and Value Chain Expert

Key Achievements

- 15. Successfully conducted baseline survey; the Knowledge Attitudes and Practices (KAP) survey and Market Survey
- 16. Successfully organized project training activities in coordination with implementing partners
- 17. Oversaw the training of project beneficiaries in standard operating procedures for food safety and adherence to high quality standards
- 18. Technically advising the renovation and operational organization of 2 fish shops to meet food safety and public health standards, including the development of HACCP manuals and induction of members to the same
- 19. Maintained good working relationships and involvement of county and national government offices
- 20. Developed and applied project monitoring tools such as the Logical Framework
- 21. Supervised and coordinated all project staff

• November 2014 - April 2015: Emergency Response Trainers, Training coordinator and Environment Associate

Kev achievements

- 22. Set up knowledge management systems such as the website and social media platform accounts and maintained the same and general communication with stakeholders and clients
- 23. Successfully organized and facilitated occupational health and safety training for existing clients in areas such as first aid, fire safety, general statutory occupational health and safety training for committee members etc
- 24. Developed and successfully implemented a marketing strategy managing to make contact with over 500 potential clients, making over 100 leads and making actual sales worth over one million Kenya shillings within three months on the job.
- 25. Strengthened organizational capacity aids in bidding for and winning consultancy contracts
- 26. Led implementation of environmental services projects by the company
- 27. Supervision and coordination of subordinate staff

• April 2011 October 2014: Eco - Ethics International Kenya, Programs Officer

Kev achievements

- 28. Designed and oversaw successful implementation of over six donor-funded community projects of a combined value of about 50,000,000 Kenya shillings
- 29. Developed the first organization-wide M&E system with technical assistance from development partners and took responsibility for its operation

Page | 4

- Led the design and implementation of the Health, Safety and 30. Environment Consultancy wing of the organization
- Managed to establish and strengthen relationships with all relevant key government agencies and donor partners that was pivotal in the fulfillment of the organization's mandate
- Led the development of a vibrant internal policy environment for Page 15 the organization and was the technical brain behind tremendous improvements in organizational capacity

Led the technical team that developed the medium term strategic plan for 2014-2018

Jan. 2006 - April 2007: Leeds High School, Teacher of English (untrained)

Kev achievements

- Mobilized students and staff to field a basketball team in the official basketball competitions for the first time in 2006
- 35. Contributed immensely to the improvement in academic performance of the school

Select Publications

- Impact of Indigenous Knowledge on Kaya Forest Management as the Miiikenda bv Kenva"http://www.publishresearch.com/download/127
- "Lead poisoning in Owino Uhuru Slums in Mombasa Kenya" http:// www.publishresearch.com/download/128

Newspaper Articles

- Kenya needs a new land policy The Standard newspaper on 26th February 2009
- "University Colleges Face Uncertainty The Standard newspaper on 19th February, 2009
- Stop Treating Women Like Special Citizens" the standard newspaper on 6th October, 2009

References

- Kolikho Dan, Executive Director, Emergency Response Trainers ltd and West Ambulance Ltd; E-Mail: danwanjo@gmail.com Tel +254-723-445526, Immediate supervisor, Emergency Response Trainers
- Kwamboka, Elvira HSE Manager, **EGMF** Kenva, E-Mail: ekwamboka.egmfk@forrestgroup.com +254-714-780890. Tel Immediate supervisor, EGMF
- Saul Muvasi, **HSE** Manager, Petro Oil (k) Limited email:saul@petrokenya.petrogrp.com Phone:+254705803645 (Contact Person and supervisor)
- Dr. Okeyo Benards, PhD. Executive Director, Eco Ethics International Kenya. Email okeyob@yahoo.com Phone +254 722208676 (former boss and lecturer)

Declaration

I, Abraham Masinde Wangila, the undersigned, certify to the best of my knowledge that the information given herein is the true reflection of my ifications and experiences.

A.M. Wangila

Page | 6